LayoutInFlater
1) Trong file nguồn có ghi thế này:
Instantiates a layout XML file into its corresponding {@link android.view.View} objects.
Nó dùng để inflate (bơm, nạp… :smiley: ) cái phần XML (Phần giao diện) vào View.
Giả sử bạn muốn tạo một cái view, thì để biết cái view đó đang chịu trách nhiệm phần giao diện nào (XML) thì bạn phải inflate cái XML đó vào view.
Một trường hợp rất thường gặp là khi bạn hiện thực CustomAdapter cho ListView. Trong method getView(), bạn cần phải inflate cái XML (ở đây là layout cho item) vào biến convertView thì ListView mới biết là phần giao diện nào của item cần được thể hiện ra màn hình.
Lớp LayoutInflater này rất hữu ích nếu bạn dùng để tạo giao diện linh hoạt (có thể thêm bớt các view vào root view) chỉ bằng code thuần
2) In simple word LayoutInflater class is used to instantiate layout XML file into its corresponding View objects. 
   In other words, it takes as input an XML file and builds the View objects from it.
   LayoutInflater is mainly used for dynamic layout.
=======
*Instead of using more technical words, I will tell you in simple and understandable words.
By inflating an XML file you are getting a reference to the XML file and the various view objects like TextView,EditText view etc that are present in the XML can be converted into Java objects so that you can do various operations with them.
For Eg: Let us consider an XML file that has 1 button, 1 textview.
So now you inflate the XML file like this,
View v = inflater.inflate(R.id.somelayout,parent,false);
where R.id.somelayout is the layout that you would want to inflate. Now since you have a reference to the XML file in a View object you can now access the 1 button and the 1 textview that is present in the XML file like,
* when you run setContentView(layout file name), you can run findViewById(id of the widget). You dont need to do something like xyz.findViewById. 
The context of your app is set to that layout file and all findBiewById call will refer to that layout file.